<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A testimony against drunkenness and swearing, &amp;c. With a postscript unto all such as have any tenderness of heart or conscience, either male or female, or any fear of God in you, and are grieved at the abominations that you daily hear and see amongst your families and neighbours, in what country or nation soever. Being a copy of a paper written and given forth (at Polch-Ground within the Haven of Long-Sound) in Norway (the 20th of the fifth moneth, 1674.) in the king of Denmark's dominion. / By William Bayly.</title>
            <author>Bayly, William, d. 1675.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1675</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 7 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 4 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A76272</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B1539</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R170481</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">45578140</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 45578140</idno>
            <idno type="VID">172100</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A76272)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 172100)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2614:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A testimony against drunkenness and swearing, &amp;c. With a postscript unto all such as have any tenderness of heart or conscience, either male or female, or any fear of God in you, and are grieved at the abominations that you daily hear and see amongst your families and neighbours, in what country or nation soever. Being a copy of a paper written and given forth (at Polch-Ground within the Haven of Long-Sound) in Norway (the 20th of the fifth moneth, 1674.) in the king of Denmark's dominion. / By William Bayly.</title>
                  <author>Bayly, William, d. 1675.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>7 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[S.l. :</pubPlace>
                  <date>printed in the year 1675.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Friends' Library, London.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Temperance --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Swearing --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:172100:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A TESTIMONY AGAINST Drunkenneſs AND SWEARING, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>With a <hi>Poſtſcript</hi> unto all ſuch as have any Tenderneſs of Heart or Conſcience, either Male or Female, or any Fear of God in you, and are Grieved at the ABOMINATIONS that you daily hear and ſee amongſt your Families and Neighbours, in what COUNTRY or NATION ſoever.</p>
            <p>Being the Copy of a Paper written and given forth (at <hi>Polch-Ground</hi> within the Haven of <hi>Long-Sound</hi>) in <hi>NORWAY</hi> (the 20th of the fifth Moneth, 1674.) in the KING of <hi>DEN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MARK</hi>'s DOMINION.</p>
            <p>By WILLIAM BAYLY.</p>
            <p>Printed in the Year 1675.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:172100:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:172100:2"/>
            <head>To a People much given to Drunkenneſs AND SWEARING, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>A <hi>Viſitation</hi> and <hi>Warning</hi> from the Lord God of Heaven and Earth, unto all you <hi>Drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kards,</hi> who are ſtrong to drink Strong Drink, and who drink till ye are inflamed there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, and your Tongues utter Folly and Perverſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, glutting your ſelves with the Good Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of God, and Abuſing them which are given to be received in his Fear with Thankfulneſs, and to be uſed in his Wiſdom, and in Moderation, to his Glory; for which End all things were made and created,; and not to be Conſumed and Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted upon your Exceſſive Luſts, to the Diſhonour of God (and the Name of <hi>Chriſtianity</hi>), and to the Grieving his pure Spirit (his Witneſs in you), which you make merry o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er, and trample under foot the Pearl of great Price, worſe then the Swine and Beaſts that periſh, whilſt many of your poor Fellow-Creatures are ready to Starve and
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:172100:3"/>Periſh for Want. Do ye think or believe there is no Juſt God, who will Reward every one ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his Deeds done in his Body, or that ye ſhall not be called to an Account for theſe things? How dare you take his Holy Name in your Mouthes, and profeſs your ſelves to be <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> who are ſo filled with Wickedneſs, &amp;c. as, <hi>Oaths, Lying, Drunkenneſs, Sottiſhneſs, Pride</hi> and <hi>Vanity,</hi> exceeding the <hi>Turks, Infidels</hi> and <hi>Heathens</hi> in your Abominations, who will riſe up in Judgment a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt you in the Day of your Account?</p>
            <p>Wo unto the DRUNKARDS of <hi>England, Holland, Norway, Sweedland</hi> and <hi>Denmark,</hi> ſaith the Lord God, who beholds your Sottiſhneſs, Bru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſhneſs, Deceit and Abominations, who have greatly Abuſed his tender Mercies, and make a Wrong Uſe of his Long-ſuffering and Kindneſs towards you by theſe your Doings; and ye have no Cloak for your Sins; but Condemnation is your Portion, and Wo and Miſery will be your End forever, without ſpeedy Repentance.</p>
            <p>What Lamentation ſhall I take up for you, O ye Rebellious and Stiff-necked People, who live in Fulneſs, Pride and Aboundance of Idleneſs! The Sins of <hi>Sodom</hi> (whom God deſtroyed) do even cry againſt you,<note place="margin">Iſa. 20.</note> (as <hi>Iſaiah</hi> did againſt the Drunkards of <hi>Ephraim</hi>), <hi>Wo to the Crown of Pride, to the Drunkards of</hi> Ephraim; <hi>they ſhall be trodden under foot, even the Crown and Pride of the Drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kards of</hi> Ephraim: <hi>Ye have Erred becauſe of Wine, and are out of the Way becauſe of Strong Drink: The
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:172100:3"/>Prieſt and the Prophet have erred becauſe of Strong Drink; they are ſwallowed up with Wine; they have gone aſtray through Strong Drink; they fail in Viſion; they ſlumber in Judgment; for all their Tables are full of filthy Vomitings; no Place is clean.</hi> Thus did that Holy Man of God declare againſt their Sottiſhneſs, Drunkenneſs, Pride, Exceſs and Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleanneſs, as moved of the Lord, by his holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, in his Day; and thus am I moved of the God of Heaven at this time to declare againſt you, and to warn you all, both Prieſts, Rulers and People, in whom the ſame Beaſtlial Life &amp; Ungodly Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctices are found: Ye are an Evil Example in your Generation, and you grieve God's Spirit, and cum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber his Ground worſe then the Fruitleſs Fig-tree; and a Stink you will be to Poſterity, and your Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morial will be an Abhorrence through Ages to the Upright in Heart, and your End will be Ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Deſtruction and Miſery, if ye Repent not ſpeedily; <hi>the Lord hath ſpoken it.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:172100:4"/>
            <head>Poſtſcript.</head>
            <p>AND now unto all you that have any Ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs of Heart or Conſcience, either Male or Female, or any Fear of God in you, and are grieved at the Abominations that you daily hear and ſee amongſt your Families or Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, in what Country or Nation ſoever you are.</p>
            <p>This is the Counſel of the Lord unto you, Stand Still, be Still and Low in your Minds, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline your Heart and Ear to that which you feel grieved in you; for its the Seed that God loveth, that is Oppreſſed and Burdened with the Filthy Converſation of the Wicked; its pure, and clean and holy; Defilement grieves and burdens it, as <hi>Lot</hi> in <hi>Sodom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Therefore in Patience wait, in pure Hunger and Thirſt after Righteouſneſs, in the Fear of God, Low and Tender, and in due time Deliverance will come to his Choſen: Therefore faint not, thou Worm <hi>Jacob,</hi> thy Helper is near thee: Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed are the Poor in Spirit, theirs is the Heavenly Kingdom of Everlaſting Reſt, Peace &amp; Comfort.</p>
            <p>So, believe in the True Light, which manifeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth and reproveth Sin and Evil, and obey it, that thou mayeſt become a Child of Light (as Chriſt ſaid) an Heir of Light and Life of the Promiſes
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:172100:4"/>which are all in Chriſt Jeſus, the <hi>True Light of the World, which lighteth every one that cometh into the World;</hi> and ſo will the Darkneſs vaniſh away and thy Bondage, and thy Soul be freed from the Thraldom of the Power of Satan; and then thou wilt Praiſe the God of thy Salvation in the Land of the Living: Therefore conſult not, reaſon not with Fleſh and Blood, which muſt never enter God's Kingdom; neither be diſcouraged at Hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips and Tryals; look not out at any Viſible Things, but to the Inviſible God alone for Help, the Everlaſting Hill from whence Salvation co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth; feel it near thee, thou Tender One; for unto thee this is the Counſel and Words of the Lord, who is no Reſpecter of Perſons, but <hi>in every Nation whoſoever feareth God &amp; worketh Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, is accepted of him,</hi> and none elſe; for <hi>without Holineſs no man ſhall ſee the Lord in Peace.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>W. B.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
